<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/rss/styles.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>tjex.net - posts</title><description>Programmer and creative technologist.</description><link>https://tjex.net/</link><atom:link href="https://tjex.net/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"/><item><title>logging the monkey mind</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/logging-the-monkey-mind/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/logging-the-monkey-mind/</guid><description>A new style of logging that sits somewhere between a diary entry and a social media post.</description><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 16:16:07 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;As of &lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/logs/04V01&quot;&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt; I&apos;m trialling a style of logging that sits somewhere between a
social media post and a diary. This will be taking place over at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/logs&quot;&gt;logs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? I&apos;m putting effort into making this site more of an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/#this-site&quot;&gt;artefact&lt;/a&gt;, rather than a digital business card and
accompanying blog to illustrate that I&apos;m still alive. So in keeping with that
goal, logging a (filtered) &lt;a href=&quot;https://mntre.com/reform.html&quot;&gt;monkey mind&lt;/a&gt; could be
a value over time so that
(a) you, the reader, may stumble across some interesting links, ideas, notions or
comedy and (b) I, the monkey, have a record of my fleeting thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think having this record online will maintain &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; sense of thoughtfulness and
tact, and with the added side effect that I can also access them the
internet - as it does happen where I recall something cool I saw but am not on
my own machine to find the link in my history or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sysid/bkmr&quot;&gt;bookmarks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>admin</category></item><item><title>Why use the Arvelie time system?</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/why-use-the-arvelie-time-system/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/why-use-the-arvelie-time-system/</guid><description>Why use an alternate time system? Because it carries more meaning.</description><pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2024 17:24:13 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve implemented the Arvelie time system, which I found documented &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.xxiivv.com/site/arvelie.html&quot;&gt;here on
Devine Lu Linvega&apos;s site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote my initial thoughts on the time system in, &lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/posts/the-arvelie-time-system&quot;&gt;The Arvelie time system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why actually use it? Particularly, when I, unlike Devine do not live on a
boat and do need to exist much more rigidly within the dark ages of the Gregorian calendar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me it&apos;s for two main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Treating the beginning of a project as year 0 creates a closer relationship
to the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This site is not a news site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Arvelie time offers a much cleaner framework for project planning
and time management. In the Gregorian calendar a &quot;month&quot; of work can be anywhere
between 28 to 31 days. A &quot;month&quot; in Arvelie is 14 days, always.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A closer relationship to a project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website is a personal project. Not just the source code, but the projects,
posts and artefacts that get presented on it. I am also a personal project
(WIP). 2020 was the year when my direction in life began to steer in a very
different direction (moving from a life in music to a life in software
development).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strangely enough, before any of that was apparent, and before
Covid-19 hit, I had started a physical journal mid 2019 and titled in Paradigm
Shift. I later &lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.bandcamp.com/track/paradigm-shift&quot;&gt;released the music I was making at the
time&lt;/a&gt; under the same title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By embedding the age of a project within time, time itself becomes a member of
the project, rather than its usual function -- a tool to categorize and sort all
historical and future events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I developed that impression very quickly when browsing through Devine&apos;s website.
Seeing time stamps in Arvelie communicated the progression of the work
within the context of the Devine Lu Linvega / xxiivv project, rather than a
universal point in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice side effect is that the connotations of a timestamp is also removed. If I
see a timestamp somewhere in the range of 2020-2022 I think &quot;Covid-19&quot;. On
Devine&apos;s site 2020-2022 would be represented as 14A00-16A00.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes that context can bolster the character of a work. But other times
it can hinder it. When browsing a blog for example, it&apos;s easy to go back a year
or two and begin to characterise the posts as &quot;old&quot;, even though the topics may
be completely relevant or even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; relevant -- it&apos;s no secret that to see the
future, we need to look into the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arvelie time allows for a less &apos;flavoured&apos; interpretation of the artefact, and
brings Time on board as a project member, rather than a standard universal
measuring stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;This site is not a news site&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The posts I&apos;ve made so far may include some references to current
happenings, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/posts/prehistoric-ai-learning&quot;&gt;learning in the prehistoric age of AI&lt;/a&gt;,
but I&apos;m not reporting on events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this, regular dates are not nearly as important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, Arvelie time maps perfectly to the Gregorian calendar. It&apos;s just a
cleaner way to divide up spans of time. I built an &lt;a href=&quot;https://git.sr.ht/~tjex/arvelie&quot;&gt;Arverlie
converter&lt;/a&gt; that I use in all my blog and diary
templates. In my &lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/logs&quot;&gt;logs&lt;/a&gt; I reveal the regular date if
you hover over the Arvelie time stamp on an individual log page, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/logs/04V01&quot;&gt;log
page for today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, technical blog posts would not be suited for Arvelie time. People
need to know the date of a technical post to get an idea of how outdated the
tools now are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly in the web domain or when learning a new tool or language, things
move so fast that a technical tutorial a year or two old can land you with in a
sub-optimal or completely dated solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>The Arvelie time system</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/arveelie-time-system/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/arveelie-time-system/</guid><description>The Arvelie time system is a concise and useful way to approach our relationship to time, and also time management.</description><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 13:33:08 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m currently wrapping my head around the Arvelie time system, which I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.xxiivv.com/site/time&quot;&gt;here on Devine&apos;s website&lt;/a&gt;,
(after also having it
bent by his &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.xxiivv.com/site/horaire&quot;&gt;time tracking system&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since writing this post, I decided to try implement Arvelie into my
journaling and have written &lt;a href=&quot;https://git.sr.ht/~tjex/arveelie&quot;&gt;a CLI helper for converting to and from
Arvelie&lt;/a&gt; for any that are interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two things I really like about the time system. One, that time ranges
are uniform. Each month has 14 days, which creates 26 months. This makes time
management feel much more approachable. And two, that time for any project or
moment, begins at 0. So Arvelie time is always relative to the artefact which it
is logging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a different relationship between us and time. As we no longer have
a positional relationship to the past. That is, the past that came before year
&quot;0&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is mostly how we measure time anyway. How old are you? How long have you
been programming? For people into computers, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_time&quot;&gt;Unix
time&lt;/a&gt; follows this same concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically when conceptualising a date or time, we additionally reference it
against &quot;time immortal&quot; (which in some domains has the suffixes &apos;BC&apos; and &apos;AD&apos;).
This meaning, we&apos;re in the year 2024 now, and can recognise how much things have
changed in the last 150 years (even without having been alive then).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&apos;s different in Arvelie time. If you&apos;re, 24 now, then what we know as the
year 2000, would for &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; be the year 0. This creates an interesting and
alternate feeling about the past. It feels more like each birth (organic, or
otherwise - like a project) is its own strand of time, sprouting from the true
&quot;time immortal&quot;, which does not have a start date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this can sound a bit wishy-washy, I would argue, that this is a lot more
accurate given the context in which we live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we actually measure time in the same style as Arvelie - the universe is
(by our best measure) about 13.8 billion years old. Meaning, that the big bang
was year 0. However, I&apos;m writing this in the year 2024. Or more interestingly,
I&apos;m writing this in the year 2024AD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is interesting to me, because the BC / AD attribute, directly communicates
an understanding that time is infinite (or that it moves more like an
oscillation). This is one of the few aspects of religion that I actually like.
That infinity is maintained as a truth, rather than a concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although, granted, this has all too often been used as a weapon (heaven and hell
for eternity). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/4/24120352/israel-lavender-artificial-intelligence-gaza-ai&quot;&gt;But we turn all sorts of good things into
weapons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>Learning in the prehistoric age of AI</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/prehistoric-ai-learning/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/prehistoric-ai-learning/</guid><description>To what degree do we actually learn with AI tools? And will those of us who turn to these tools, be condemned to a bleak reality once the AI bubble pops?</description><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 20:31:38 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;A significant issue with AI learning is how easy it is to gloss over the
question of, &quot;why?&quot;. &quot;Why ...&quot; is the generated answer a good answer? The
generated solution may work, but we have no knowledge of how it compares to
other solutions, nor the process of getting to the solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s also a loaded situation, asking the LLM to explain why it&apos;s proposing any
given solution, because the LLM &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; has the right answer EVEN WHEN IT
DOESN&apos;T. Total smoke and mirrors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recalling an answer happens in part because we recognise the context of a
problem: we&apos;ve seen the problem before, or at least part of it is familiar to
us. Reinforced pathways in our brain get fired, and our memory of how to
construct the solution get called into our working memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staring bewildered at a code editor will not etch any pathways of learning into
our mind. In fact, it&apos;s more likely to train an association between the feeling
of confusion and stress, and the action of reaching for the LLM. Like what
coffee or bus stops are to smokers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, trying to work out solutions (i.e, the act of &quot;problem solving&quot;)
does reinforce neural pathways. Reaching for a quick answer does not. We may
still learn, but it&apos;s a fickle learning experience, and one that may well fade
quickly from memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s not do different from searching Google in place of books, or spell
correction in place of searching through a dictionary. There&apos;s no need to learn,
because we can get it done faster with a tool. Auto-correct or the searching
Google once again for that basic information may be one thing, but where do
&lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; draw the line for learning your career skills as developer, lawyer,
writer, doctor...?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prophecy Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why, in some number of years, and if AI technologies really do embed
themselves in our workflows, I think there will be a divergence of two broad
segments of the workforce. There will be those who can understand, conceptualise
and materialise solutions to problems or creative ideas without AI tools, and
those who cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the culture of the world will look like then though, I don&apos;t have an
equally prophetic claim. Either there will come a time where people who have
maintained their mental faculties will become in incredibly high demand, or
they, the &quot;meat heads&quot;, will be left to menial tasks, while the &quot;silicon heads&quot;
churn through their tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s another. The AI bubble could pop. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dDUC-LqVrPU&quot;&gt;AI capabilities could
plateau&lt;/a&gt;. This would leave us with
only mediocre tools that may well remain close to their current state. If this
is the case, the &quot;silicon heads&quot; will have to reckon with the hardest lesson of
their time: how does one &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; make a paper clip? (And then proceed to
craft 1 paper clip).&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>learning</category><category>society</category><category>career</category></item><item><title>Maths in code, code in music, and music in code</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/maths-code-and-music/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/maths-code-and-music/</guid><description>As I get more comfortable with programming, I&apos;m starting to see more and more parallels between my old life and my new one.</description><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 14:58:58 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The other day I again encountered the statement that I must be good at maths if
I&apos;m able to read and write code. I myself remember thinking the same of
others. And it was actually a contributing reason why I never considered
learning programming earlier on. I just figured I wouldn&apos;t get very far, as
I don&apos;t have the best of love stories with maths...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as I chip away at LeetCode in preparation for the post uni job hunt, I&apos;ve
come to realise why a relatively good grasp of maths does go a long way. But it
doesn&apos;t necessarily come down to being able to calculate, more so the type of
mental gymnastics that maths requires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would argue there are two main skills that get trained when practicing maths
that help a lot with reading and writing algorithms; keeping multiple values in
your head while you think, and recognising patterns. The problem is, unless you
did maths throughout school (and enjoyed it enough), there aren&apos;t really any
other opportunities to practice this kind of skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;On a High Level&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I noticed this pattern the more I reviewed the LeetCode submissions that &lt;em&gt;far&lt;/em&gt;
outperform the rest. Those submissions are typically written using single
letters as variables, but &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; achieve the correct result with pure
mathematical computations and logic (instead of using data structures), which is
why they&apos;re so performant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this I see the translation of mathematics into programming at the
surface level. Of course, there are &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; levels deeper where serious skills in
maths are required to solve hard problems with code (e.g, encryption).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it was interesting to recognise the value of maths, even when not performing
any mathematical calculations. The ability to keep a track of values assigned to
variables is applied in other areas of life as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Code in Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my long term goals is to understand how my previous life in music
composition can integrate into my new life as a programmer on a cognitive level,
rather than a creative one. It&apos;s interesting to think how I took the ability to
read music as a completely unrelated skill. And equally, how I figured I would
just always hate maths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though it&apos;s been a while, I can still get a general idea of what the above
music sounds like just by looking at the score above. Music notation is itself
code. I would say it&apos;s easier than the code of programming languages, because to
put it simply, music notation deals with &lt;em&gt;constants&lt;/em&gt;. Every marking on that page
will always communicate the same intention, time signature in 2/4, everyone
plays &quot;very loud&quot; on bar 9 (not 0 indexed), the squiggle means to not play for
one beat, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interpretation of the score is however a &lt;em&gt;variable&lt;/em&gt;. This is what
a conductor does (to some degree). Their job is to coordinate the orchestra, but
they also give their own flair or interpretation to certain areas of the
score. They operate within a fairly limited range of possibilities. They can&apos;t
change notes, but rather guide the energy and timing of the orchestra, which is
enough to make some performances of the score stand out from others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things get a little more towards programming with the score below (Stockhausen).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what&apos;s called a &apos;graphical score&apos;, and was pioneered by composers like
Stockhausen. It carries over similarities from classical notation, but
introduces its own &lt;em&gt;syntax&lt;/em&gt; as well. Often, the symbology would be described in
an accompanying document to the score. But other times (not necessarily in
Stockhausen&apos;s case as he was a complete control freak), it would be left very
abstract and open for interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&apos;s interesting about graphical notation, is that you almost need &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt;
musical training to be able to interpret it. This is because when we look at
a score like the one above, we can more or less pick out a &lt;em&gt;narrative&lt;/em&gt;, as it&apos;s
laid out left to right and incorporates angles, curves, shapes and shadings that
evoke at the very least a feeling of natural forces at play. Gravity, inertia,
momentum, friction and fragility can all be identified in the image. And we all
at some level know what heavy, rough, light, fast or hollow objects may sound
like in any particular environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Constants, Variables, Syntax and Narrative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I consider the above, what stands out to me is that between programming
languages, maths and music, there are many shared components: &lt;em&gt;constants&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;variables&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;syntax&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;narrative&lt;/em&gt;. These components simply hold different
values, given different domains. Sound and movement for music, numbers for
maths, and data for code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think if I&apos;d been aware of this back in school, that there is much more
fluidity between skill sets than is immediately apparent, I wouldn&apos;t have
convinced myself that maths and programming were two completely impossible
things for me to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I for one will never suggest to my children that they have a &quot;creative&quot; OR
&quot;analytical&quot; mind, like I was told. It just doesn&apos;t work like that, and creates
a belief in an impressionable mind, that there are two paths, and they can only
walk one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>philosophy</category><category>psychology</category><category>learning</category></item><item><title>You don&apos;t need luck, luck needs you</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/you-dont-need-luck-luck-needs-you/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/you-dont-need-luck-luck-needs-you/</guid><description>Luck is an inherent part of life, it&apos;s not a requirement or a special trick for success.</description><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 12:59:21 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Luck is what happens when preparation meets opportunity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seneca (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&quot;&gt;disputed&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often someone will describe success as requiring a collection of abilities
including, but not limited to: determination, dedication, an open mind,
structure, healthy habits, practice, focus, etc. But what seemingly &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt;
get&apos;s included is &quot;a little luck&quot;.&lt;br /&gt;
I find this a bit annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luck is a given. To the point where it&apos;s redundant. You&apos;re lucky to even be here
in the first place. I myself owe my existence (in large part) to a coin toss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980&apos;s, a young Australian writer was travelling through Greece and
boarded a ferry with the intention of visiting Naxos. She went up deck, spotting
a man whom she asked to hold one of her bags, while she went back downstairs to
get the other. The man came from a small town in Germany, and was on a work
trip, conducting seminars in Jazz drumming and rhythm. Once back up, and after
some time conversing, the man asked if she would come with him to Paros. The
lady, being an excited companion to the twists and turns of life, tossed a coin.
Heads for Paros, tails for Naxos. As luck would have it, it landed on heads. And
so I&apos;m here today writing this post, and for the sake of a nice story, can
report my parents are happily together to this day, and that my mum still has
the coin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m by no means suggesting that being born is your best shot at success. That&apos;s
called privilege, the dark shadow of luck. Instead, I&apos;m wanting to point out
that luck is so pervasive, so integral to life, that it&apos;s redundant to include
it as a pre-requisite for success. In other words, luck is an inherit
consequence of being spawn of this universe. Every day we play the game of
chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, forget about your endeavours needing to depend on luck. Instead, rid your
mind of the worry and get busy, so that when luck does reveal itself, you can
seize it. Naturally, luck can deliver unexpected ease to a goal. But it&apos;s not
predictable, nor is it controllable. It&apos;s therefore a waste of time and energy
to worry about &quot;good&quot; or &quot;bad&quot; luck coming your way. Ever heard someone comment
on a past happening as a &quot;blessing in disguise?&quot;. Luck is then a question. Can
you recognise it when it comes your way, and will you be prepared when it does?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/317947/wired-to-create-by-scott-barry-kaufman-and-carolyn-gregoire/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wired to Create&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
Kaufman and Gregoire recount how opportunity and preparedness forged a
crystalline unit of luck, sending Albert Hofman on a bike ride he would never
forget.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his 1983 memoir
&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/lsdmyproblemchil0000hofm_g1j0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;LSD: My Problem Child&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
Hofman wrote, &quot;I could not forget the relatively uninteresting LSD-25&quot;, &quot;A
peculiar presentiment...induced me, five years after the first synthesis, to
produce LSD-25 once again so that a sample could be given to the pharmacological
department for further tests.&quot;[^1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the final stages of crystallizing the sample that would be sent to the
department, the smallest of doses dropped on his hand, making him feel a bit
strange and go home sick. This case of chance piqued his curiosity and on April
19, 1943 Hofmann ingested an &quot;infinitesimal dose&quot; of LSD and while riding home
on his bike from the lab, experienced the first acid trip ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;In the realm of scientific observation, luck is granted only to those who
are prepared&quot;&lt;/em&gt; - Louis Pasteur&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&apos;t need luck, luck needs you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]:
Kaufman, S. B. and Gregoire, C. (2016), Wired to Create: Unraveling the
Mysteries of the Creative Mind. p.59-60&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>Writing a masters thesis with Zettelkasten - Part 1</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/writing-a-masters-thesis-with-zettelkasten-part-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/writing-a-masters-thesis-with-zettelkasten-part-1/</guid><description>How can we use Zettelkasten effectively, given a large and time sensitive writing and research task such as a thesis or Ph.D?</description><pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 11:57:30 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve finally arrived on a topic for my masters thesis. It&apos;s an investigation
into how the Zettelkasten system enables creative ideation, and subsequent
development of a network graph user interface, which will be optimized for that
end goal (generating ideas).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This topic stems from my life long interests in psychology and technology and as
such, is a very exciting endeavour for me and my Zettelkasten. Naturally there
will be a lot of reading, thinking and writing to do, and it would be a crying
shame for that thinking and writing to not end up in my Zettelkasten as notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until now I haven&apos;t had to use my Zettelkasten for a large piece of writing.
The largest so far being my
&lt;a href=&quot;../2023/floss-a-partial-antidote-to-social-catastrophe&quot;&gt;essay on open source and social catastrophe&lt;/a&gt;,
but I only used my Zettelkasten to review relevant literature notes and write a
few new ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my masters thesis, I&apos;m exploring what is effectively uncharted territory for
me. Additionally, the thinking will need to go much deeper than the essay
required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how can we use Zettelkasten effectively, given a large and time sensitive
writing and research task such as a thesis or Ph.D? There are a few documented
experiences of this process, such as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/posts/field-report-4-what-i-learned-writing-thesis-with-zettelkasten/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L9SLlxaEEXY&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, which I&apos;ve taken some
cues from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest fear for me is the question we all dealt with when trying to first
understand Zettelkasten; how do we find a specific note again? I will be reading
and writing notes on a lot of new content. The process and timeline will be very
focussed and tight, I therefore would benefit from having my notes at hand all
the time. Chasing after lost notes would be frustrating and time consuming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, Zettelkasten isn&apos;t designed to be a reliable search and recall system,
it&apos;s designed to be an environment where we stumble upon previous ideas in
contextually relevant and therefore meaningful ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt;In the old system, the question is: Under which topic do I store this note?
In the new system, the question is: In which context will I want to stumble
upon it again?&lt;/em&gt;&quot; &lt;br /&gt;
~ Ahrens, Sönke - How to Take Smart Notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&apos;t want to be stumbling around all the time... This project requires
some more stability in note recall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task then is to establish some system of keeping track of which notes I&apos;m
working on that are specific to my thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Thesis Structure as an Index Note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had already made a rough plan for the structure of my thesis, which included
section headings, sub headings, and dot points for the intended content and
questions to be addressed. I realised this would make for an excellent
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/#structure-notes&quot;&gt;index/structure note&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the sections and sub-sections had questions that were to be addressed
within them. These questions immediately become question notes. The question
notes are then filled with outbound links to position and ultimately argument
notes. This process of question, position, argument documentation is a mixture
of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.cumincad.org/data/works/att/ca71.content.pdf&quot;&gt;the IBIS method&lt;/a&gt;,
the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/posts/layers-of-evidence/&quot;&gt;Three Layers of Evidence principle&lt;/a&gt;
and what&apos;s referred to as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://oasislab.pubpub.org/pub/54t0y9mk/release/3&quot;&gt;QCE&lt;/a&gt; (although I have no
idea where that acronym comes from).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate, here&apos;s a sample of the index note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
title: ctech masters thesis
date: 2024-01-02
id: ip4r
tags: [index]
aliases:
---

# ctech masters thesis

Driving motivation for the practical project:

As creative technologists, it is essential to have tools that help us generate
creative ideas and solutions, not just tools that are used to build the end
product.

## Research questions

Investigating these research questions:

- [what defines the Zettelkasten system?](../kp4q)
- [how does the Zettelkasten system promote creative ideation?](../8sb8)

... more questions / links to notes

## 2. Introduction

### 2.1 Creative Ideation or Knowledge Generation?

- [Is there a distinction between creative ideation and knowledge generation?](../../4w2l)

... more questions / links to notes

### 2.2 Zettelkasten and Systems Thinking

... more questions / links to notes

etc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Diary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as this,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/posts/zettelkasten-grid-system-organisation/#d-for-diaries&quot;&gt;I keep a daily diary within my Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt;
where I can write freely about particular project or &lt;em&gt;Zettelkasten related work&lt;/em&gt;
at hand. It&apos;s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a diary of my personal life, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of a daily note&apos;s content related to my thesis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# 2024-03-18

Addressing the question
[what connections are there between the Zettelkasten system, creative ideation and network graphs?](../../it61).
Trying to think about how zk and graphs are complex systems, and how creative
ideation is the result of those systems. How does that happen? That
[consciousness occurs when colonies of cells are large enough in number and connections](../../k8pg)
is an interesting angle, but in the case of zk, the notes aren&apos;t &apos;interacting&apos;
with themselves per se. Rather, it is the interaction within the mind, of the
information they hold, that somehow comes together to create an idea.

Idea&apos;s are generated from borrowing parts of pre-existing information.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tags&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per
&lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/posts/zettelkasten-grid-system-organisation/#structure-tags&quot;&gt;my approach to tagging&lt;/a&gt;
I will tag all notes that are deemed strongly related to my thesis with
&lt;code&gt;#p/thesis&lt;/code&gt; (&apos;p&apos; for project). This is partly a crutch to help find a lost note,
but is particularly useful given my Zettelkasten program of choice,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zk-org/zk&quot;&gt;zk&lt;/a&gt;, has many powerful features via the command
line. Having all my thesis notes filterable by tag, means that I can batch
process them in all ways imaginable from the command line (eg, archival, ML
input, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moving Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, I have this process and setup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An established thesis structure outline, which acts as an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/#structure-notes&quot;&gt;index note&lt;/a&gt; where I
can insert and create links to notes under section headings. This is similar
to filing notes into folders, just much less rigid. One link can be placed
under multiple headings too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A daily diary where I can write free form thoughts while linking notes that
I&apos;m referring to. This keeps track of my half formed ideas if I can&apos;t manage
to write a proper note about them, or if the thoughts are too abstract and
undefined for a note. These are often called &apos;fleeting notes&apos;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Following the iterative process of making a &lt;em&gt;question note&lt;/em&gt;, which links to
many different &lt;em&gt;position notes&lt;/em&gt; (possible conclusion to the question), which
ultimately links to an &lt;em&gt;argument note&lt;/em&gt; (the final conclusion to the
question). By following this process, I can keep track of multiple ideas that
relate to any one initial question, which helps in developing ideas. It also
fosters good thinking processes in general and will help keep the content of
the thesis clearer and easier to understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A broad based filter and search capability via the shared &lt;code&gt;#p/thesis&lt;/code&gt; tag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s see how it goes! I&apos;ll write part 2 at some point down the track and review
how this system performed, how it changed, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>learning</category></item><item><title>The GRID System for Frictionless Zettelkasten Organisation</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/zettelkasten-grid-system-organisation/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/zettelkasten-grid-system-organisation/</guid><description>The GRID system is a framework for frictionless organisation of a Zettelkasten. It defines a set of rules for note creation and note tagging that suppress the need for content categorisation.</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2024 19:01:33 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The GRID system is a framework for frictionless Zettelkasten organisation. It
defines a set of rules for note creation and note tagging that suppress the need
for content categorisation. The goal is to strike the balance between cognitive
friction when writing, and observability when managing, searching, reading and
navigating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of content categorisation is the question, &quot;Which topic does this
note relate to?&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lack of categorisation helps reduce cognitive friction (not losing the train
of thought) and promotes a focus on the core principle of how the Zettelkasten
method creates value, inter-note linking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system was designed with two main concepts in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keeping things simple and following a few well defined principles is the best
technique to deal with complexity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content categorisation is the main cause of cognitive friction when working
within a Zettelkasten.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some advice is also given for practices which support the goal of a
&quot;frictionless system&quot;, such as metadata suggestions and file naming with Unique
Identifiers (UIDs), but they are not directly part of the GRID system itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post got very long, so you can also jump to the &lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot;&gt;conclusion&lt;/a&gt;
to get more of an overview before diving in if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#back-story&quot;&gt;Back Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#overcategorisation-is-the-death-of-a-zettelkasten&quot;&gt;(Over)categorisation is the death of a Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-fundamentals&quot;&gt;The Fundamentals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#my-requirements-for-the-system&quot;&gt;My requirements for the system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-grid-system&quot;&gt;The GRID System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tagging&quot;&gt;Tagging&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-metadata-file-naming-and-future-proofing&quot;&gt;Note Metadata, File Naming and Future Proofing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back Story&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years I&apos;ve read through many ideas of how to structure and
organise a Zettelkasten vault. The difficulty of this hangs in the balance
between the need for &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; structure, but the truth that too much structure can
severely hinder the effectiveness of a Zettelkasten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;A good structure enables flow&quot;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
... &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&quot;The best way to deal with complexity is to keep things as simple as possible
and to follow a few basic principles.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
...&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&quot;The biggest threat to creativity and scientific progress is therefore the
opposite: a lack of structure and restrictions. Without structure, we cannot
differentiate, compare or experiment with ideas.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;~ Ahrens Sönke, How To Take Smart Notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bitter sweet reality of any organisational technique is that we don&apos;t know
how well it works for us until we spend some time working with it. After many
iterations, this system emerged and has remained unchanged for quite some time;
I have a solid feeling that I&apos;ve found what works for me and feel it&apos;s robust
enough to present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope it provides some value to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;(Over)categorisation is the death of a Zettelkasten&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial foray into the Zettelkasten technique is uncomfortable. It goes
totally against the grain of how we were taught through school to take notes.
One notebook per class, divided into semesters / classes / topics / ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of note taking solidifies as &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; way we record knowledge for
ourselves, and so does the structural thinking that goes behind it,
categorisation. This is the real problem.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/wired-for-categorization/&quot;&gt;We&apos;re hardwired to categorise&lt;/a&gt;,
and we use it for everything, libraries, music, art, ethnicity, psychological
disposition, physical state. An adjective is a categorisation. We categorise to
try and create &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; structure within the chaos of of reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when we access memories, or follow a train of thought, we rarely do so by
using rigid categorisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prompt, &quot;recall all memories that relate to the house I grew up in&quot;, does
not return &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; the memories of your childhood home. It will most likely
return the image of your childhood home as it exists in your memory, but it
will inadvertently return memories &lt;em&gt;linked&lt;/em&gt; to your childhood home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Zettelkasten system, information is linked together by a &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; context,
meaning from one note to another, and each note is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.andymatuschak.org/Evergreen_notes_should_be_atomic&quot;&gt;atomic&lt;/a&gt;.
Trying to categorise for retrieval down the track, quickly leads to
over-categorisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why I think starting with the Zettelkasten technique is daunting, and
also why it&apos;s hard to find a system that works, because we&apos;re so used to the
crutch of categorisation, but categorisation is the antithesis of the
Zettelkasten system&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/posts/no-categories/&quot;&gt;^3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a total lack of structure, let&apos;s say a singular folder full of all notes,
without tags, without titles and without dates... This is chaos. By definition,
there is a balance to be struck, hence the task of finding a system that works
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;Without structure, we cannot differentiate, compare or experiment with
ideas.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;~ Ahrens Sönke, How To Take Smart Notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Fundamentals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, I highly recommend to read up a little on Niklas Luhmann&apos;s
original Zettelkasten method &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; churning through the swathes of different
approaches within a digital Zettelkasten (this post included). Understanding the
fundamental principles of anything before delving into developments built on
top,
&lt;a href=&quot;../2023/fundamentals-all-the-way-down&quot;&gt;greatly enhances our evaluation of those developments&lt;/a&gt;
(whether they be ideas, technologies, relationships, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zettelkasten.de&quot;&gt;Zettelkasten.de&lt;/a&gt; is undoubtedly the most precious
resource for that. Christian and Sascha communicate the topic with such
excellence, and the forum there is also full of great discussion and attitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/&quot;&gt;introduction to the Zettelkasten method&lt;/a&gt;
is a great jumping in point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A brief review of other systems in the wilderness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, the deliberation of how to give some structure to a Zettelkasten
system boils down to how and in what degree to use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;folders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;note titles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;note ids&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;naming conventions (e.g., including symbols)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;note metadata (keywords, aliases, author, contextual stimulus, modification
date, ...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest traps for over-categorisation are folders and tags. The GRID system
deals with these specifically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other formalised systems I&apos;ve seen predominantly mentioned within
Zettelkasten related forums, videos and posts are
&lt;a href=&quot;https://johnnydecimal.com/&quot;&gt;the Jonny Decimal System&lt;/a&gt;, Tiago Forte&apos;s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://fortelabs.com/blog/para/&quot;&gt;PARA system&lt;/a&gt;, Nick Milo&apos;s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p0zWJ-TLghw&quot;&gt;ACCESS system&lt;/a&gt; and Bryan Jenks&apos;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/wB89lJs5A3s?feature=shared&amp;amp;t=1115&quot;&gt;ADHD wrangler&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve integrated all of them to considerable degrees except the Jonny Decimal
system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Folders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned systems primarily try to formalise a directory structure for
note storage. Within a Zettelkasten system, folders don&apos;t create a major hurdle,
as we can link across folders. This leads many (including my past self) to make
the mistake of building a folder structure, that only ever gets deeper. And as
the folder structure gets deeper, we also become more invested in it and begin
to rely on it as search tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the biggest issue with folders is that it creates cognitive friction
during note creation. &quot;Where do I store this note?&quot; should never require thought
or time navigating a directory structure. This is a design feature of the GRID
system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonny Decimal, PARA and ACCESS are based on a categorisation of directories, but
I find the categorisation to miss the mark for various reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jonny Decimal is limitless in its directory structure depth ( categorisation
granularity). That&apos;s a rabbit hole. &lt;em&gt;Way&lt;/em&gt; too much cognitive friction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PARA is designed with project managers in mind. The folder structure is
incongruous with Zettelkasten principles, e.g., the &quot;Archives&quot; folder. A
Zettelkasten &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an archive. A note is never &apos;inactive&apos;, just as a memory
never is; they&apos;re both just resting for a moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ACCESS comes closer to a frictionless solution of folder management, but the
&quot;Extra&quot; and &quot;Spaces&quot; folder are again rabbits holes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The one true value of folders for a (digital) Zettelkasten [^2]&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a physical Zettelkasten, folders have next to no relevance (Luhmann did keep
his reference notes in a completely separate box [^1]), but they can be very
useful (but still not required) in a digital system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a digital system we have the power to work with tools such as scripts, full
text search and regex. Folders are powerful parameters for these features,
inside &lt;em&gt;but also outside&lt;/em&gt; of your Zettelkasten program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you personally don&apos;t use these tools yet, there is a good chance you
will to some degree down the track. Making design decisions based around the
future &lt;em&gt;program independent&lt;/em&gt; usage of your data is super important (called
&apos;future proofing&apos;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, what if you want to host your notes online
&lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.andymatuschak.org/&quot;&gt;Andy Matuschack style&lt;/a&gt;, but have all your
personal diaries mixed in with everything else in one folder?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&apos;d really hope that you included a &lt;code&gt;diary&lt;/code&gt; tag and that the hosting /
publishing framework can filter out notes tagged &lt;code&gt;diary&lt;/code&gt;, when publishing
online. Ignoring a folder is a very basic feature of any such framework, and
worst case, you could just provide the Zettelkasten vault with the diaries
folder removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Zettelkasten has the ability to be a life long artefact for us. Ensuring and
optimising where possible for future usability is therefore &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; important,
and a strong consideration of the GRID system. Folders help with this.
Recommendations of which folders &lt;a href=&quot;#the-grid-system&quot;&gt;are made below&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tags&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Milo and Jenks present the two common and divergent approaches to tagging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It boils down to tags as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WUq8Pun28FI&amp;amp;t=1222s&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;umbrella terms&lt;/em&gt;, to create loose associations&lt;/a&gt;
between notes, like &apos;shared hobbies&apos;, or tags as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zIh1S7ra3aI&amp;amp;t=172s&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;statuses&lt;/em&gt;, that describe the &lt;em&gt;state&lt;/em&gt; of a note&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GRID system sits strongly in the tags as &lt;em&gt;statuses&lt;/em&gt; camp, but leans a little
bit over into the other camp as well by tagging notes with their information
source (see &lt;a href=&quot;#tagging&quot;&gt;tagging&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Categorical (topical) tags follow the same pitfalls as folders; it requires an
ever increasing amount of mental energy to handle. The following thought
processes are involved in managing a group of topical tags when writing a note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;What tags relate to this note?&quot; (in other words &quot;how many ideas do I think
could possible have to do with this note&apos;s content?&quot;...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;Do I already use this tag, or do I have a tag that is similar that will
suffice?&quot; (and how quickly and efficiently can you check that you have that
tag or not?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;If I don&apos;t have anything with this tag, is it worth adding it?&quot;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;if I add it, the filtering strength for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; other tags will be
weakened&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;so, will I really think to find this note again by filtering for tag &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;,
or will it be missed entirely?&quot;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;if I add it, and don&apos;t use it, I&apos;ve weakened the filtering strength of
all my other tags for nothing&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution is to give ourselves a hard limit to how many tags each note should
be given. But this just creates an extra step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&quot;If this note deserves four tags, (because it&apos;s such an important and rich
note that it deserves to be found more easily than others), but I&apos;ve only
allowed myself three tags per note, which are the top three tags?&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This exact problem is what structure notes help to solve (see
&lt;a href=&quot;#i-for-indexes&quot;&gt;I for indexes&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My requirements for the system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system should:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;strongly facilitate &lt;em&gt;idea generation&lt;/em&gt;. It should not become a database for
simply recording and retrieving knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be as &lt;em&gt;frictionless as possible&lt;/em&gt; when creating, managing and processing
notes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Idea generation&lt;/em&gt; happens when notes are linked together meaningfully and
densely. This allows us to move fluidly through the system, replicating the
process of cognitive thought. In such a system, serendipity is often just around
the corner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;em&gt;frictionless as possible&lt;/em&gt; means picking a spot somewhere between order and
chaos. Too much order creates friction. There are too many decisions to consider
and too often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chaos occurs when there is too little order, and the system scales beyond a
certain point. There is a time factor involved, which is why committing to an
organisational design system for their Zettelkasten system is stressful - and
could well be why you&apos;re reading this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The best way to deal with complexity is to keep things as simple as possible
and to follow a few basic principles.&lt;/em&gt; ~ Sönke Ahrens, How To Take Smart
Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above quote encapsulates the way I&apos;ve evaluated design decisions for the
GRID system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Keeping thing as simple as possible&quot; is in my mind &quot;keeping things as
frictionless as possible&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should hopefully become clear in the system specification below how these
design decisions support that goal. But if it doesn&apos;t and, you&apos;d like to clear
something up, please email me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The GRID System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like PARA and ACCESS, GRID is also an acronym for the folder structure. The
acronym was a total fluke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; have another folder for projects (inspired by PARA), so it was called
the GRID-P system, or P-GRID, or GRIPD (as in the &apos;uncool&apos;, and non gamer tag
way to write &apos;gripped&apos;) ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is; the acronym did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; define the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;G for glossary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For notes that serve no other purpose than to factually define a thing. Useful
for using as a jumping off point for a specific thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what notes do I have that I&apos;ve linked to?..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the Zeigarnik effect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chickenisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adam Curtis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recursion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This helps to avoid context switching (cognitive friction). If we can&apos;t remember
what a certain thing is, we can quickly refresh our memories within the same
system. Navigating to a glossary note returns us the facts that most interest us
and which we may be able to add to, given new knowledge we may have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposite process is opening a browser or book, searching for information and
in the process shifting our mental context and, after &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; amount of time, losing
our focus entirely (particularly if you&apos;re searching through the internet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These notes can also serve as mini-indexes if we wish (see &apos;I for indexes&apos;
&lt;a href=&quot;#i-for-indexes&quot;&gt;below&lt;/a&gt;), by including a small selection of valued notes that
relate to the glossary term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;R for reference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes on content we read, watch, hear. Termed &apos;literature notes&apos; in many
discussions. The folder is titled &lt;code&gt;reference&lt;/code&gt; to aid in frictionless filing: If
we&apos;re consuming some information and writing notes on it, it goes in the
&lt;code&gt;reference&lt;/code&gt; folder - it doesn&apos;t matter if it&apos;s a video, recording, academic
paper, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good example of where to withhold the temptation to create more
folders. We could make &lt;code&gt;Reference/Papers&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Reference/Videos&lt;/code&gt;, etc. But it&apos;s
again a rabbit hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often have we come across a research publication and tried to determine
whether it was a &apos;paper&apos; or an &apos;academic journal article&apos;... Poof! There goes
our train of thought. Not worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are different styles of making reference notes.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.zettelkasten.de/discussion/2002/concrete-example-of-literature-notes&quot;&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt;
shows the common variations (I use &apos;alternative approach B&apos;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I for indexes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I consider indexes, Luhmann&apos;s
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/#structure-notes&quot;&gt;structure notes / hub notes&lt;/a&gt;
and Nick Milo&apos;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WUq8Pun28FI&quot;&gt;MOCs&lt;/a&gt; as
fundamentally the same; they are notes pertaining to a particular topic, with
outgoing links to other notes of value, on that topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, some of my index notes are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cognition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Meditation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A brief case for structure notes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structure notes strike a functional balance between folders and tags. They
provide a topical starting point, e.g., &quot;Cognition&quot; along with some linked notes
relating to &quot;Cognition&quot;. But the structure note requires us to insert a link
manually, and each time we go to do that, we &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; what other notes are
&lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; linked. As we view the pre-existing links in the index, we develop a
perception as to how valuable it is to add the new link. Compare this with
adding a tag, whereby we have no immediate idea of how the current note we&apos;re
tagging compares in value to other notes tagged &quot;Cognition&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result of curating index notes is that each time we decide to search through
our Zettelkasten by a category (by opening an index note), our direction is
already thoughtfully predefined by our past selves, using our own thought
processes to inform &lt;em&gt;what we define as good focal points for that category&lt;/em&gt;.
This helps maintain our current velocity of thought, and provides much less
friction in deciding which note to select when compared to doing a tag search
for &quot;Cognition&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;D for diaries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With dates as titles. A place to write down fleeting information or personal
entries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;(And the rest of the notes...)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exist at the root level, from where they may sprout and grow into
&lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.andymatuschak.org/z5E5QawiXCMbtNtupvxeoEX&quot;&gt;evergreen notes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tagging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, tagging in the GRID system focuses on describing the &lt;em&gt;status&lt;/em&gt; of a
note, with a small exception for reference and glossary notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like folders, tags must never describe the concept matter of the note. It does
not scale and creates friction when writing notes (thinking about what tags to
assign), as mentioned &lt;a href=&quot;#tags&quot;&gt;above&lt;/a&gt;. Instead, tags communicate either what form
the &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt; of the information is or what the &lt;em&gt;status&lt;/em&gt; of the note is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Source tags&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Through which communication medium was the information received?&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;audio:&lt;/em&gt; music, sound recordings, podcasts, discussions, debates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;image:&lt;/em&gt; visual art, photography, graphical content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;text:&lt;/em&gt; anything text based; book, paper, research, publication, blog post,
newsletter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;me:&lt;/em&gt; thoughts that arise from &apos;nowhere&apos; (dreams, sudden thoughts)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;video:&lt;/em&gt; (moving images) film, documentary, news reports&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, some edge cases exist. In &lt;em&gt;my personal interpretation&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a music track on Youtube is tagged &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a music video on Youtube is tagged &lt;code&gt;video&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notes with a source tag, should therefore &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; have an accompanying
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zettelkasten.de/introduction/#reference&quot;&gt;reference entry&lt;/a&gt; at the bottom
of the note.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reference note on a book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
tags: [text]
---

# Title

Body of the note

---

References:

- url to external source.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s also nice to have an outbound back-link if the note was created out of
direct inspiration from the content of another. But for this there is no tag, as
such a tag will become almost all encompassing and therefore offers next to no
practical value for filtering (this also means it will destroy your graph view
if you use one). Simply adding the reference without a tag will then suffice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
tags: []
---

# Title

Body of the note

---

References:

- [The note that inspired the creation of this note](./note.md)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Status tags&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;seed&lt;/em&gt;: all notes start with this. It&apos;s a way to easily search for unrefined
ideas. A note is a &lt;em&gt;seed&lt;/em&gt; if it has less than 3 meaningful links.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;fern&lt;/em&gt;: assigned upon removal of the seed tag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;evergreen&lt;/em&gt;: when a &lt;em&gt;fern&lt;/em&gt; has 5 or more meaningful links.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard this terminology through Bryan Jenks. I like the symbolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The status tags are great aids in Zettelkasten maintenance. We can filter our
notes by &lt;code&gt;seed&lt;/code&gt; tag, and pick some to work on, iteratively promoting them to
ferns or discovering they already are, and the tag just didn&apos;t get updated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bi-product of this process is stumbling across old ideas and connecting them
under new context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the old system, the question is: Under which topic do I store this note?
In the new system, the question is: In which context will I want to stumble
upon it again?&lt;/em&gt; ~ Sönke Ahrens, How to Take Smart Notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This further invalidates the &quot;Archive&quot; folder in the PARA system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Structure tags&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;index&lt;/em&gt;: an index note for a specific topic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;project&lt;/em&gt;: an index note for a specific project (I have one for my masters
thesis).
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As this is also an index note, it gets saved in the index folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;glossary&lt;/em&gt;: all notes in the glossary folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of these tags is purely functional. They provide an alternate and
typically quicker way way to access or filter these notes as apposed to
navigating to the &lt;code&gt;index&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;glossary&lt;/code&gt; folders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having notes in folders in addition, allows for a much simpler process when
handling or accessing the files outside of the Zettelkasten app
&lt;a href=&quot;#the-one-true-value-of-folders-for-a-digital-zettelkasten&quot;&gt;see above&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Note Metadata, File Naming and Future Proofing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The below are recommendations of mine and not explicitly part of the GRID
system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Metadata&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What metadata to use in notes and what file naming convention to implement does
come down to personal requirements and also what program we&apos;re using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My general recommendation for metadata is in keeping with the principles of the
GRID system: as frictionless as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means as little metadata as possible. I have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
title: note title
date: creation date
id: the file name without extension
tags: [tag, tag]
aliases: e.g., &apos;AI&apos; (for the note Artificial Intelligence)
---
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is already too much for some. But for me it&apos;s fine because &lt;em&gt;no matter what
type of note&lt;/em&gt;, those metadata fields are applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reference notes I have an extra &lt;code&gt;people&lt;/code&gt; field, as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is a useful search filter (e.g., for researchers or authors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the tag name is immediately obvious (the authors name), so there&apos;s no
cognitive friction to add it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is not a tag, and therefore does not pollute my tags list (this is
important, particularly if you&apos;re an Obsidian user and like to display your
tags in the graph view).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;File Naming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As hinted at in the above metadata, I use UIDs as file names (4 character
alphanumeric, lower case). This is for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it reduces all friction of providing a good file name (the program creates the
UID for me...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the file name never needs to be changed
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this will prevent link breakage (also if notes are referenced from other
apps).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this will force you not to use the note&apos;s filename as natural language in
your sentences, as if your program updates link titles for you this
[[sentence]] will become ridiculous if the &lt;code&gt;sentence.md&lt;/code&gt; is renamed to
&lt;code&gt;chicken.md&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;links remain small and tidy when viewing in a raw format (I write in neovim)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;files are super easy to locate and process if needed
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locating the file &lt;code&gt;s5wf.md&lt;/code&gt; in my file system is laughably easier than
&lt;code&gt;cool...AI...note.md&lt;/code&gt;, as I have 20+ notes with &apos;AI&apos; in the title.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/zk-org/zk&quot;&gt;zk&lt;/a&gt; which handles UIDs incredibly well.
Notes are created with a title and are searchable and linkable by that title,
but the file name itself can be a UID. The notes title can be changed of
course, which will make it searchable by that new title, but all pre-existing
links will stay intact, as it&apos;s linked by the file name, which is the UID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a far cry from Obsidian&apos;s UID functionality (I used Obsidian happily
for years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Future Proofing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&apos;Future proofing&apos; relates to how well a system will keep working through the
development of the surrounding technologies (computers, storage mediums,
operating systems, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also relates to switching costs, which is how well a system can keep
operating when it is transferred immediately into a new environment. E.g.,
changing your note taking app or operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of a Zettelkasten (repository of markdown documents), I would list
these practices as contributing heavily to future proofing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;only use programs that work with &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; markdown files (meaning the files are
on your own computer and can be accessed by you outside of the app without
restriction)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no spaces in file names: &lt;code&gt;file-names.md&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;file_names.md&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no special characters in file names except hyphens and underscores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no spaces in tags with multiple words: &lt;code&gt;tags-with-multiple-words&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not using programs that have syntax that differs from standard markdown spec.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lower case letters for directories (if you ever progress to using the terminal
or writing programs, this will save you a lot of head and finger ache).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;critically review any features that you bring into your workflow that are
program specific (such as Dataview in Obsidian)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use open-source software as it will not disappear overnight or put up a
paywall that you either cannot or will not want to pay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GRID system is my attempt to strike the balance between cognitive friction
when writing and observability when managing. The folder structure deals with a
clear separation of concerns (glossary, references, indexes and diaries) while
the tags target the &lt;em&gt;object class&lt;/em&gt; of a note&apos;s &lt;em&gt;source&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;status&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;structure&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provides a level of future proofing that can pay off hugely in the long run
and constrains the level of complexity and management costs that very easily
arise when the amount of topical tags become too many (not to mention the
eventual &lt;em&gt;reduction&lt;/em&gt; in observability).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GRID system can therefore be implemented and used as is, but also built upon
very easily if needed. This allows for a custom system with a strong foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: https://luhmann.surge.sh/communicating-with-slip-boxes, Section II, point 3.
[^2]:
Thanks to Christian in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.zettelkasten.de/discussion/comment/19357/#Comment_19357&quot;&gt;Zettelkasten.de thread&lt;/a&gt;
for pointing out that I&apos;d only described &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to use folders, but now
&lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>learning</category></item><item><title>The Noob Chronicles - Chapter 1</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/the-noob-chronicles-chapter-1/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/the-noob-chronicles-chapter-1/</guid><description>It&apos;s been two years since I learnt what a for loop was. How&apos;s it been going since then?</description><pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 19:48:11 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s important to step back and get some perspective about your progress with
any skill. And considering the mammoth idea of taking a career side step into
programming, and my general high expectations for myself; I thought to begin a
post series titled &lt;em&gt;The Noob Chronicles&lt;/em&gt;, where I look back in time since the
last chapter and review what&apos;s happend since then. This is the first chapter and
I&apos;m &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going back to birth...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music, Art and For Loops&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s been two years since I learnt want a for loop is. Since then the ball has
been rolling with great joy, but cracks are appearing on its surface. I heard
quite early on that the more you learn, the more you realise how much you don&apos;t
know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve never felt this more than with programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In music and art, a lot of your technique, creativity and craft is hidden, in
that the &quot;source code&quot; of a music file or image output is not observable. There
is often no reference material at all for the public to unpack how you made that
content. And often, there can also be no material for yourself to look back on
(as in the case of improvised music or setups using a modular synthesiser which
no longer holds the same patch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In programming, the technique and craft of others is very often visible due to
open-source development, but also tutorials, APIs, and internal code bases. And
as you start to learn, you start to understand parts of what you&apos;re looking at,
but become very much aware of how much you have no clue about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference here between arts and programming, is that the process of
learning to program has much larger gaps between moments of gratification. Or
put otherwise, the hurdles are larger and further in between than when making
music and art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With music and art, it more often than not feels good all the time. Playing
music in particular creates a symbiosis between your body (playing the
instrument), your mind (accessing your creativity, memories and emotions) and
your environment (hearing the result of body and mind, echoed into the room).
Actually, this is why it&apos;s very hard to be even a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; singer. It takes &lt;em&gt;a
lot&lt;/em&gt; of training to listen to the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; sound and pitch of your voice and to
correct it, as apposed to hearing what you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; your pitch is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With programming, you are not given so much leeway. Usually things just don&apos;t
work &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;; Like opening your mouth to sing and excrement just spraying out,
bouncing off the wall and hitting the fan, leaving you standing dumbfounded in a
brown haze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this topic, I wrote how I think
&lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/posts/a-case-for-polishing-your-tools&quot;&gt;polishing your tools is a good thing&lt;/a&gt;. It
discusses how tinkering, or hacking on your setups or tools can actually teach
you a lot. And this is valuable. But each little optimization or little bug fix
in your setup also allows for much smaller spans of time and effort between
moments of gratification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s very true, that learning to code can happen much faster if you can apply it
within a project that you are invested in - in the case of the above post,
Neovim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Filling in Gaps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hardest thing in my programming education or me has been filling in the
gaps. As stated, I first learnt what a for loop was two years ago, and this was
at the start of my masters degree. It&apos;s not a computer science masters, but a
very large part of it deals with programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m studying a Masters of Creative Technologies, which essentially gears you up
to be a highly proficient operator at the interaction of technology, media and
art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal trajectory though, is to become a software engineer, and I want be
as good as I can be. As I completed my various class assignments, moving through
python, JavaScript, c++, Java, lua and fields of graphics, audio, interaction,
networking, machine learning, cyber security, web development and games, I
became chronically aware of how many foundational elements were being glossed
over or skipped entirely. This is natural of course. The more things learned in
a given amount of time, the more superficially they will have to be learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fill the gaps, I went searching for drop in replacements for full computer
science knowledge. This lead me to resources like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bottomupcs.com/&quot;&gt;Computer Science from the Bottom Up&lt;/a&gt;, an online web
version of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sarabander/sicp&quot;&gt;Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs&lt;/a&gt;,
and of course the well known
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nand2tetris.org/&quot;&gt;Nand to Tetris series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Progress has however been slow. I&apos;ve finished my course work as of July this
year, so have only had enough brain space since then to start looking at
learnings outside my own masters courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m also gradually chipping through
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3735293-clean-code&quot;&gt;Clean Code: A Handbook of Agile Software Craftsmanship&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gopl.io/&quot;&gt;The Go Programming Language (book)&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.algorist.com/&quot;&gt;The Algorithm Design Manual&lt;/a&gt; and waiting for me is a
dense beast I got for free titled
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/internetworking-with-tcpip/9780137464197/&quot;&gt;Internetworking with TCP/IP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back Patting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t want to come across as a self righteous prick now. But I do want to put
my skill progressions into perspective. For myself to look back on, and also any
other person also grappling with the huge initial learning curve of programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So please read this like you&apos;re reading my personal diary. In a large sense,
that is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://tjex.net/posts/hello-world&quot;&gt;what this blog is&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after learning what a for loop is, I programmed the below image. So it
would be the first thing I ever programmed; an illustrious and provocative work
made with Processing4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then I&apos;ve...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implemented machine learning algorithms that
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tjex/pdf-correlator&quot;&gt;provide useful information&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;built a tool that I&apos;ve wanted to have for at least eight years, a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tjex/ofTombola-sequencer&quot;&gt;Tombola Sequencer&lt;/a&gt;, written in
C++.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;worked with others to build a continuous integration server from scratch on a
Raspberry PI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;become markedly proficient with Neovim and just weep with joy with how god
damn easy it is to work with text and files compared to before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;built my own website from scratch &lt;em&gt;and actually make conscious design
decisions that I follow through on&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;studied a full semester of computer science at one of the most notable
engineering schools in Europe (KTH, Stockholm) and survived.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;became proficient with git and feel safe and confident to try out changes
quickly and deeply within my projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;become comfortable reading and implementing API documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learned my way around JavaScript, Python, Go, HTML, CSS, Lua and Bash to a
degree that is on average between functional and mediocre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solved a real world creative problem with code during an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tjex/WOMB-Installation&quot;&gt;artistic project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reinvigorated my musical side and creative palette with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://tidalcycles.org/&quot;&gt;TidalCycles&lt;/a&gt;, allowing me to do things that are
otherwise incredibly arduous or complex otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;made useful contributions to real world open-source projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;manually setup an encrypted install of Artix Linux and used it as a daily
driver, until I got sick of poor hardware performance compared to my M1 Mac...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;researching into topics of distributed systems, conflict-free replicated data
types, ActivityPub, LoRaWAN, Multi-agent systems and pattern generation for my
masters thesis - and can actually comprehend what I&apos;m reading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Until Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main goals / tasks from here are to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish my masters thesis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learn algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learn JavaScript, Go, Node and Flutter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up my Machine Learning skills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learn about distributed systems and the respective technologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s see what happens up until chapter two!&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>career</category><category>learning</category></item><item><title>A Case for Polishing Your Tools</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/a-case-for-polishing-your-tools/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/a-case-for-polishing-your-tools/</guid><description>Polishing your tools is a good thing. It can teach you a lot, particularly if you&apos;re new to a technology or practice. Just keep track of how far down the rabbit hole you are.</description><pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 09:31:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I have a lust in understand things to a deeper level than what is needed to
actually implement or use the thing. &lt;em&gt;How deep&lt;/em&gt; is a question for each learning
or interest in question. There is always a trade off between productivity and
capability. Do you just implement and move on without knowing anything about
what just happened, or do you dig in so hard that you end up only reading and
not implementing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe the fundamentally correct answer to this is that your behaviour should
&lt;em&gt;shift&lt;/em&gt; within the bounds of that spectrum at any one time. If you&apos;re falling
too deep, dig your hands and feet into the walls of the rabbit hole to halt your
fall, scurry back up a little, and enter one of the horizontal tunnels you fell
past. Rinse, repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone new to programming, I was given some &quot;OK buddy&quot; treatment when
excitedly advertising to more experienced programmers that I was switching to
Neovim from VSCode. It&apos;s a large hurdle to overcome for sure. But the investment
is paying dividends. Not only can I work with files and file systems &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt;
faster, but I&apos;ve accidentally learned many fundamental programming concepts and
practices through polishing my tool (Neovim), that even if I were to switch to a
different editor now, it would have still be worth the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the case of someone who&apos;s starting out. They know next to nothing about
reading and implementing APIs, debugging, program flow or sourcing, managing and
working with packages, binaries and configuration files on their system. That
was me, and still is to whatever degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That person can teach themselves all of that through building their Neovim setup
&lt;em&gt;from scratch&lt;/em&gt;. Anyone who opens up a bare bones Neovim/Vim install is
&lt;em&gt;compelled&lt;/em&gt; to polish it, &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt;. It looks awful and feels completely unusable.
But in reality, it&apos;s a sandbox in which to play. It&apos;s easy to work iteratively
and interactively, and it results in having a tool that greatly enhances your
ability to work with code and your system (yes, even debugging). And it&apos;s fun to
do it! The moments of gratification are much closer together. In this sense, it
becomes a &quot;personal development environment&quot; (PDE, as apposed to IDE), as
explained by TJ Devries in his video,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QMVIJhC9Veg&quot;&gt;PDE: A different take on editing code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only this, but working with Neovim keeps you closer to the command line.
This has also taught me a lot. I greatly enjoyed getting over the intense
feeling of danger when using the command line. And the power and value it
brings! Steve Yegge comments on this at length in one of his
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mb8ayJEsnk8&quot;&gt;tech talks&lt;/a&gt;. Doing things in the
command line uncovers a lot of knowledge too, in the same way as Neovim does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, why does moving a file with &lt;code&gt;mv&lt;/code&gt; run so quickly, while copying it
with &lt;code&gt;cp&lt;/code&gt; runs much slower? The path to answering this question isn&apos;t as clear
if you work with a file manager, or do the moving and copying via the file
browser of your IDE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the shell, there are many fewer layers of abstraction. You&apos;re operating in a
space further down the rabbit hole, where information is more raw and questions
are as a result more clear. Searching &lt;em&gt;&quot;why is mv faster than cp?&quot;&lt;/em&gt; will lead
you to much richer information than &lt;em&gt;&quot;why does copying files in Finder, take
longer than moving them&quot;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you may dig into &lt;code&gt;cp&lt;/code&gt; a little further and come across &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt;, and find that
it&apos;s a better program for many copying tasks. From there you may well polish
your tool (shell config) a little more and make an alias for it like
&lt;code&gt;alias rsync=&quot;rsync -vrPlu&quot;&lt;/code&gt;. Now your speed is further optimised by not having
to type the flags you always want, and your cognitive load is lower by not
having to remember or search for those flags in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you may want to alias some other frequently typed commands. Now you have
enough where you refactor them out into a separate file and source it in your
&lt;code&gt;.zshrc&lt;/code&gt;, which requires you to learn a bit of bash syntax, which leads you to
writing little utility scripts that run fast and do whatever you want, because
it runs in the shell and the shell is the lowest level interface between you and
the computer. Your computer becomes a much more powerful tool for you, and it&apos;s
nicely polished so that you &lt;em&gt;move fast&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;freely&lt;/em&gt;. That&apos;s ace!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever someone says &quot;polishing your tools is a trap, it&apos;s a bad thing&quot;,
they&apos;re speaking of the extremes. Polishing your tools
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9gUatBHuXE0&quot;&gt; can be a great thing &lt;/a&gt;. It&apos;s
helped me learn a good amount of base knowledge in an engaging environment and
rewarding environment. No-one wants to use a rusty hammer that gives them
splinters, particularly if they can learn things a long the way by polishing and
sanding it. As with everything, self control, moderation and keeping an end goal
in mind is key.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>learning</category></item><item><title>Fundamentals all the Way Down</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/fundamentals-all-the-way-down/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/fundamentals-all-the-way-down/</guid><description>How deep do you start when stepping into a new field of learning? Do you learn the fundamentals, or get up and going as quickly as possible?</description><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2023 19:17:01 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I recently listened to an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://changelog.com/jsparty/283&quot;&gt;episode of The Changelog&lt;/a&gt;, that dealt with
the topic of whether it&apos;s important or not as programmers to understand the
fundamentals of the technology, and if so, how many layers deep should we go?
Does a web programmer only need to understand the framework they work with, or
should they understand the browser as well? Or the translation from JavaScript
to V8, or TCP/IP, or .. or .. or ..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h6&gt;turtles (fundamentals) all the way down (&lt;a href=&quot;https://i.pinimg.com/originals/96/5d/7b/965d7b06172081b5ece135eda09aad89.jpg&quot;&gt;src&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s a topic that&apos;s definitely on my mind as I move into a career as a
programmer. Particularly as I&apos;m &quot;late&quot; in the &quot;game&quot; after having spent the
majority of my life in music and sound, the question of time allocation carries
significant weight. Will learning deeper right from the start, pay off down the
track? And if so, how deeply to begin? I hear people state that everyone should
learn Assembly because it gives you a much clearer idea of how a computer works.
Similarly, the course &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nand2tetris.org/&quot;&gt;Nand to Tetris&lt;/a&gt; has been
recommended to me multiple times by different people. Both of these learnings
can be argued as fundamental, deeper layers. This is in contrast to boot camp
style courses that teach you in quick fire fashion, the functions, syntax and
specifics of a programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both approaches have their merits. And that&apos;s of course the total simplicity in
the answer. I think it just depends on how much you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to learn. And it&apos;s in
this idea, that I think the original question of how deeply we should understand
something, became confused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Different Styles of Travel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a feeling that in today&apos;s age, many people just want to know what the
minimal amount of work is, in order to achieve a goal. That could be getting a
job, passing an exam, getting an interview, etc. Somehow the path to getting
somewhere has become a means to an end, and not a part of the end; if there was
an option to skip the whole process of getting there, and to just suddenly be
there, I feel that many would take that option (e.g. the temptation that ChatGPT
stokes). This also goes for actually physically travelling somewhere. There are
few people I know who have any appreciation for &quot;the scenic route&quot;, or who
attribute little if any truth in the idiom, &quot;travel is not about the
destination, it&apos;s about the journey&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me personally, digging deeper into whatever I&apos;m learning is something I
enjoy. It makes the journey sweeter. But it can also become a distraction from
actually generating output. This was a constant and massive battle back when I
was making music. The balance between learning new tools and making music with
them was a fine and precarious line. The TL;DR at this point, is that balance is
key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Transitional Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m two weeks into a transition from Mac to GNU/Linux (hereafter in this blog,
Mr Stallman, for the sake of sanity, referred to as, &quot;Linux&quot; [^1]), and chose to
start with a base Arch Linux install. Starting (deeper) with Arch Linux was
difficult, but it&apos;s already paying off, making a good example for this post.
Being required to install absolutely everything and configure where needed, has
not only given me a much greater appreciation for the computer as a piece of
technology, but it&apos;s also provided me a glimpse into the larger &quot;space&quot; that
programmers work in; the potential connections, present and future, that exist
between programs as data flow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interoperability and openness of Linux are what spurred me to change from
Mac. But in addition, these characteristics have unexpectedly given me access to
a kind of &quot;playground&quot; where I can explore the inner workings of a system to a
degree that wasn&apos;t available to me before. This will quite clearly be beneficial
for my skill sets as a programmer, and I don&apos;t believe I would&apos;ve realised this
&quot;playground access&quot; with such clarity, had I not tried to make it harder for
myself by starting with Arch, and instead started with a full desktop
environment install like KDE, Mint, Manjaro, etc (i.e the non-scenic, &quot;just get
there now&quot; route).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I say learn the fundamentals where it fits, but it doesn&apos;t have to be as low
as possible, and straight from the start and only ever moving higher. Learning
isn&apos;t linear, it twists and folds back on itself, filling space where we don&apos;t
even realise there was space to be filled. Taking the example of web development
again; I think just learning React and hitting the job market is skating on thin
ice. As is mentioned in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://changelog.com/jsparty/283&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; linked
in the first paragraph of this post, people who take this route typically have
no idea what to do when something breaks. This isn&apos;t great for longevity in any
career - unless that breakage becomes a stimulus to learn something new. Then
the learning folds back on itself and you take a step deeper, getting closer to
some kind of fundamental layer underneath where you currently are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]:
I&apos;d love to give both Stallman and Torvalds simultaneous credit when
writing, but GNU/Linux just didn&apos;t stick. Sorry. Marketing language sucks,
but it happens. The heard lets some things stick, and some things not.
https://www.gnu.org/gnu/incorrect-quotation.en.html&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>career</category><category>learning</category></item><item><title>First 10 Day Vipassana Course</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/first-vipassana-course/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/first-vipassana-course/</guid><description>A few thoughts after my first 10 day silent meditation course in the technique of Vipassana and a consolidation of its philosophies.</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2023 18:51:08 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;Vipassana&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vipassana is the original, unaltered meditation technique of &quot;The Buddha&quot; (as we
were taught, any enlightened person is Buddha), Siddhartha Gautama. It is a
practice of meditation that is universal in that everyone has access to it. You
don&apos;t need to pay someone to provide you with your own special mantra (no access
for the poor), to visualise an image (no access for the blind), or to sit or
move in any particular way (no access for physically challenged). The technique
is grounded in experiencing the present moment through observation of bodily
sensations, something that everyone has access to [^1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following is my understanding of the philosophies of Vipassana meditation
and how they interface with our daily life and nature as a whole. As context,
you can read a text &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhamma.org/en/about/art&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; based on a talk
by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhamma.org/en/about/goenka&quot;&gt;S.N Goenka&lt;/a&gt;, who was a leader in the
teaching of Vipassana from 1969-2013. A base point for any further inquisition
should be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhamma.org/en/about/vipassana&quot;&gt;dhamma.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I comment a little bit on the ten day course I completed in June 2023, but in
keeping with the correct way of introducing people to the course - I do not want
to influence too much or create too much of an image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TL;DR for the Vipassana course itself is that it was mentally and physically
challenging but invaluably educational and rewarding. The two advices I would
give is 1) anyone considering to undertake a course should first establish at
least a loose practice of mindfulness meditation and be comfortable to sit on
the ground with legs crossed. This is more so that you can take best advantage
of the unique experience and environment of a Vipassana course, and not have to
spend all your time battling physical discomfort. And 2) to just wait until you
feel like it&apos;s a good time to do it. There&apos;s no need to rush. It will pay off
much more if it&apos;s done when it wants to be done. In the meantime, further your
meditation practice on your own accord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meditation can be a bit tricky to get started with. I fumbled in the dark for
a while, but now have 4+ years of daily mediation behind me - this being just
a preface for extending an invitation to anyone who feels they&apos;re also
fumbling in the dark. Shoot me an email any time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Retreat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did my course in Sweden at &lt;a href=&quot;https://sobhana.dhamma.org/&quot;&gt;Dhamma Sobhana&lt;/a&gt;. The
environment was a manifestation of tranquility itself; well kept gardens, small
forest areas with varieties of beautiful flowers, winding paths and cosy red
cottages with white trim. Time is defined by the soft striking of two gongs. One
for the male students, another for the female, a perfect fourth interval apart,
creating a slowly phasing ambient rhythm that is heard anywhere in the compound.
Beds are comfortable, food is wholesome and amenities just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The noble silence was an interesting and special experience. On the arrival day,
you meet everyone and can get to know each other, then from 20:00 the noble
silence begins. The nine days that follow you may not talk or communicate with
other students in any way. No gesturing, writing or signalling. This helps a lot
with being able to stay in the meditational focus and frame of mind required to
make the meditation sessions more fluid. It also reduces the mental friction
that can occur if students compare their experiences with each other throughout
the week. This can lead to comparison between ones self and others, which has no
useful place in meditational practice at all. The meditation is your experience.
The yard stick is your equanimity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most profound thing about the silence though is, upon the last day when the
silence is lifted, how much more you know each other despite not having talked
since day one. Everyone feels like close friends. This no doubt comes through
the sharing of the challenging experience, and living in close quarters with
each other. It was very interesting to experience how a strong sense of
solidarity and friendship can still occur in near total lack of communication,
vocal or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered a few times that it could be an interesting exercise for teams of
software developers to spend some days (maybe not ten) in a retreat, where they
cannot communicate with each other at all, but need to live together and also
work on a programming task. The value would lie in the interpersonal and social
developments that come from a form of interaction that is outside of the normal
and mundane (like the uncomfortable exercise of two people being tasked to stare
for two minutes directly into each others eyes without averting their gazes.
Anyone who&apos;s done this, realises a strange sense of &apos;knowing&apos; the person
afterward, despite having exchanged no words).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vipassana retreats can be anywhere from three days to fourty-five. Ten days is
the standard and recommended length. During these ten days, you essentially live
the life of a monk or nun. You don&apos;t speak, you eat the food that is prepared
for you and you follow a set schedule of meditation and break times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s demanding, physically and mentally. Eleven hours meditation every day
requires the body to be accustomed to sitting on the floor without unbearable or
increasing discomfort. And to focus continuously for ten days is strenuous in of
itself, despite the focus not being on an analytical task. You do encounter
then, a form of mental exhaustion, and it&apos;s made worse when you indulge in
questioning how many days are left and how difficult will those days
increasingly be. But this is just as much part of the practice. To disengage
from those thoughts of aversion and craving, and the tension they bring, and to
return to the true reality of you being where you are, moment to moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Technique&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the forth day the main Vipassana technique, &lt;em&gt;Paññā&lt;/em&gt;, is taught. It&apos;s the
practice of observing sensations in the body and remaining equanimous with them.
This means to not judge them as being pleasurable or unpleasurable, desirable or
undesirable, wanted or unwanted. By practicing this equanimity, the behavioural
pattern of the mind, which seeks to generate craving (pleasure) and aversion
(displeasure), becomes weakened. The generation of craving or aversion leads to
attachment; we become attached to something desirable happening, or something
undesirable not happening. When the opposite happens, and what we want to happen
does not eventuate, we encounter misery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this, Buddha concluded that craving and aversion are the root cause of all
misery and to become fully enlightened, one must rid themselves of all craving
and aversion. At this point, a lot of people get demotivated from the
philosophy. &lt;em&gt;Enlightenment is a path only for some&lt;/em&gt;. The rest of us can move
somewhere along the path and stop at whatever point is sustainable. That is the
best collective result for society. It does not need to be all or nothing. All
or nothing doesn&apos;t help, something more than nothing does. You can still have
sex (even with yourself), or do &amp;lt;insert naughty thing&amp;gt;. The idea is to become
a &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; person, not to become Buddha. You can actually bake the cake and eat
it too in this case, you just wont assimilate into the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vipassana teaches that each and every reaction we elicit, mental or physical,
begins with a sensation in the body. The sensations in the body arise from the
unconscious mind, that is its domain; the autonomous faculties of mind and
matter. By training ourselves to calm our outer layer, the conscious mind, and
to maintain awareness of bodily sensations as they rise and pass away, we are
training an ability to integrate an awareness into our every day life. When we
subsequently find ourselves in any situation, and we have a good practice of
Vipassana established (being equanimous), we can become aware of a sensation in
the body as they occur. With the awareness of that sensation, we can then react
more wisely than we otherwise would, as our reactions otherwise would be just
that - reactions, not considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Anicca, The Law of Impermanence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this comes the emergence of a compassion for all life an all beings,
because all life, including ourselves, exists within the same universal law of
impermanence. All things change. Because all things change, all things are
impermanent, ultimate truth cannot exist in the generation of craving or
aversion. Craving &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; remain permanent, as can aversion. They feed themselves
and only grow more hungry. This is incongruous with the universal law of
impermanence. It places you on a divergent path to that of true nature, which
ultimately generates misery for you, as you are diverging yourself from nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generating craving or aversion (&lt;em&gt;sankāhra&lt;/em&gt;) is the process of desiring reality
to be something it is not. Vipassana teaches the practitioner to observe reality
as it is, which brings tranquility and peace to the experience of reality. This
does not mean that we can&apos;t desire things. Or that if we desire things or want
things to be different, that we will only generate misery. Of course in essence,
it does work this way and becomes clearer when you take the extreme as an
example: If you always desire a different reality than your own, then your
reality will be misery, because day after day, year after year it is not what
you want. This is a disease that plagues many people who are focussed on
generating wealth and power for the sake of wealth and power. It leads to never
being satisfied, because there is always more to be had. Drug addiction works
the same, it&apos;s just the object of the craving is different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can still desire things, and to be excited about things eventuating. &lt;strong&gt;The
measure of how much misery this brings to your life is how much tension you
experience waiting for the thing to eventuate and how equanimous you remain when
that desire does not eventuate.&lt;/strong&gt; If you experience no tension while waiting for
the thing to eventuate; meaning you are present in each moment up until it
eventuates or not, and if you do not react with frustration, anger,
disappointment or such when it does not eventuate; then you are living a life
closer to real peace and harmony. A life of equanimity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pure Vipassana theory would say that you should also not experience elation or
euphoria when the thing &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; occur. On the outset, this does not sound
appropriate. However, feeling elation, euphoria or other such extreme &quot;positive&quot;
feelings, are the &lt;em&gt;result&lt;/em&gt; of a craving being satisfied. If you were to feel
elation, euphoria or such feelings when the thing eventuates, you would equally
feel devastation, anger, resentment or such feelings if it did not eventuate.
With each action there is an equal and opposite reaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Sense of Realism?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is however important to remember that nature and life could not exist without
sankahra. Reproduction is fuelled by sankahra. Nature is perfect, but also
imperfect. It is cruel and kind. We can also not simply conclude that a life
completely void of sankahra which an enlightened person achieves, should be
hailed as the true destination of happiness and prosperity for all humans. If
all humans achieved this, we would stop reproducing. It would be an extinction
event. However, it would arguably be better for all other beings and plants on
earth if humans became extinct. Everything else suffers by our existence (except
diseases).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paradox here I suppose is that if all humans did become enlightened, no one
would have a problem with the human race becoming extinct within a generation,
as we would all be one with nature anyway. We would be totally and collectively
at peace with death and the ultimate truth of nature, meaning we would not be
compelled to reproduce - a partial process of immortalising ourselves by passing
fragments of ourselves down to our children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point it is theory. Just reading the concepts can never lead to an
accurate conclusion of its truth. It needs to be experienced itself. And this
comes full circle to the essence of the Vipassana technique being a universal
truth. It is a practice that is universally true for each and every human being.
The practice is to experience one&apos;s own reality as it is, not as one wishes it
to be. There is no exclusivity in the accessibility to this truth or ultimately
to enlightenment. It is universal, and nature is universal. No one is more or
less resultant from nature than anyone else. Anyone can experience the benefits
of Vipassana because everyone has universal access to the truth of nature
through the manifestation of sensations of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As touched upon, this is different from other modifications of the technique
such as transcendental meditation, which requires the practitioner be given a
mantra; a special and supposedly unique word, which only a guru can give. The
provision of this mantra, carries the burden of secrecy whereby the practitioner
cannot reveal the mantra to anyone else, or else the mantra will loose its
essence. While using the mantra as a source of focus for meditation does calm
and focus the mind, it does not allow the practitioner to access the pure truth
of themselves and their place in nature. This is because they are themselves
generating an alternate reality for themselves by repeating a secret word. This
by definition is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a universal truth. If each practitioner of transcendental
meditation is given a unique word, then each practitioner is experiencing a
reality that is divergent from their true reality when they meditate, the
reality as it is, not as they (through repetition of mantra) wish it to be. By
diverging from nature in a meditational practice, one can never truly access
nature at its core. Only the surface, a calming of the mind and an enhanced
focus, will be reached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]:
I did some research for cases where people may lose the ability to perceive
all perception of sensations in the body, but did not find anything. Only
partial loss in sensation. If I&apos;m wrong, please email me!&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>meditation</category><category>philosophy</category></item><item><title>Floss, A Partial Antidote To Social Catastrophe</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/floss-a-partial-antidote-to-social-catastrophe/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/floss-a-partial-antidote-to-social-catastrophe/</guid><description>Technology and software have together enabled immense change. Can FLOSS principals help mitigate the harm that society is enduring?</description><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h2&gt;What is the problem?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology, and in particular software, moves fast, and increasingly so.
Software interfaces with our lives on so many levels, that it becomes harder and
harder to distinguish between what is software driven and what is not. With such
saturation and speed of growth, governments and regulators have been at once
swamped by the pervasiveness of software, and due to arduous bureaucratic
process and political polarisation, condemned to moving slowly in regulating the
industry. This, combined with the allure of huge profits for the private
technology sector, has contributed to bringing forth a free-market
technoliberalist environment that promotes a &quot;strong emphasis on the failures of
regulation and government, and an effort to focus on private sector solutions to
social problems&quot;,
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/book/4956/chapter/1879816/From-Utopia-to-Practice-and-Back&quot;&gt;Benkler&lt;/a&gt;).
This is in keeping with the basic understanding of neoliberalism, but what
characterises technoliberalism is the &quot;belief that adding more technology will
eliminate scarcity and deliver prosperity for all&quot;. But has technology delivered
these promises, or will it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This essay argues that it could, but definitely not if we keep going the way we
have been. It focuses on the state we are currently in, where we have largely
lost our freedoms and agency as users of technology and how this has harmed us
as a community of communities (the public). It discusses some of the reasons why
this has happened, but in particular how this has in part been enabled by the
dominance of corporate philosophies and tactics over those of an alternative
model known as Free/Libre and Open Source Software (FLOSS).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is FLOSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free/Libre and Open Source Software (FLOSS) is the combination of two longer
standing terminologies. &quot;Free software&quot; was coined by Richard Stallman in the
early 80s after the initial hacker culture of MIT splintered, some departing to
the path of proprietary (closed source) software
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262542289/coding-democracy/&quot;&gt;src&lt;/a&gt;). The term
&quot;free software&quot; however has led to a confusion of meaning that is still ongoing
to this day leading people to interpret the term to mean software that doesn&apos;t
cost money to use. Stallman aims to clear up the confusion as such,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;When we call software &apos;free&apos;, we mean that it respects the users&apos; essential
freedoms: the freedom to run it, to study and change it, and to redistribute
copies with or without changes. This is a matter of freedom, not price, so
think of &apos;free speech&apos;, not &apos;free beer&apos;.&quot; -
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/open-source-misses-the-point.html&quot;&gt;Richard Stallman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Open source&quot; on the other hand stands for criteria a littler looser than free
software. Like free software, the source code still needs to be available for
any who wish to inspect it, but where it departs is the restrictiveness of some
open source of software (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262542289/coding-democracy/&quot;&gt;src&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FLOSS appends &quot;Libre&quot; (French and Spanish for &quot;free&quot; in the sense of freedom) to
the &quot;free software&quot; idiom in order to make clearer the true meaning of the
philosophy. It therefore offers a neutrality between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is the common alternative to FLOSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of any corporation against its competitors can often rest
significantly on the strength of secrecy behind trade secrets. The recipe behind
Coca-cola is an endearing example, as is the formula for the WD-40 multi-use
lubricant and the algorithms behind Google search or song recommendations on
Spotify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With trade secrets, companies exert competitive advantage on each other through
the defence of those trade secrets, the value of which only increases if the
company grows its market share &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the trade secret is not compromised. Once a
company claims a critical volume of market share, it becomes ever more difficult
to compete with. At this point, corporate power becomes very dangerous. With the
increase in capital from larger market share, and the power play that comes with
it (i.e, let us buy you; we&apos;ll destroy you anyway if you don&apos;t), company
acquisitions begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last two decades we have seen this pattern run rife in the technology
industry, giving birth to gargantuan monopolies such as Google, Amazon, Apple
and Meta. In the book
&lt;a href=&quot;https://chokepointcapitalism.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chokepoint Capitalism&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Giblin and
Doctorow outline how this was in part a result of Robert Bork&apos;s reinvention of
antitrust, as put forth in his 1978 book &lt;em&gt;The Antitrust Paradox&lt;/em&gt;. The Borkian
reinvention of antitrust named &quot;consumer welfare&quot; as the goal, meaning that, &quot;so
long as prices went down (or at least, didn&apos;t go up), companies more or less
stopped having to worry about antitrust enforcers showing up with subpoenas&quot;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://chokepointcapitalism.com/&quot;&gt;Giblin / Doctorow&lt;/a&gt;. The worst players in Big
Tech make their fortunes with free products (free as in, &quot;free beer&quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of technology companies, proprietary (closed source) software is the
common trade secret. Meta&apos;s recommendation algorithm for the news feed is
designed to keep you engaged
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2021/oct/03/former-facebook-employee-frances-haugen-identifies-herself-as-whistleblower&quot;&gt;primarily angry or fearful&lt;/a&gt;)
for as long as possible. The longer you are kept &apos;engaged&apos;, the more
advertisements you can be served. Reporting on the harm this has caused is
abundant with bullying, social division, depression and anxiety being
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.helpguide.org/articles/mental-health/social-media-and-mental-health.htm&quot;&gt;established themes&lt;/a&gt;
of social impact when it comes to social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2020, Meta altered its content policies to give lower rankings to content
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.helpguide.org/articles/mental-health/social-media-and-mental-health.htm&quot;&gt;they knew promoted damaging behaviours&lt;/a&gt;
but reversed it after they realised that if they changed the algorithm to be
safer, people would spend less time on the site, click on less ads, and they
(Meta) would make less money. Through actions like this it is evident that large
profit driven corporations may well care a lot for money, and little for
society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a strangeness in considering how a technology that does enable
unparalleled communication abilities for societies, can contort into a
manipulative force that has amounted to such incredible and varied harm to those
societies. But this is not the fault of Mark Zuckerberg himself, or the
employees or Meta as an entity - it is the repercussions of a value for secrecy,
restrictiveness and a technoliberal profit driven attitude towards society,
fueled by a regulatory environment of no real consequence. Meta is set to
receive the largest fine ever handed out for mishandling user information, but
as Johnny Ryan accurately puts it,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/may/21/facebook-to-be-fined-648m-for-mishandling-user-information&quot;&gt;&quot;A billion-euro parking ticket is of no consequence to a company that earns many more billions by parking illegally&quot;&lt;/a&gt;.
Fines do not make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;When Richard [Stallman] called it slavery, it wasn&apos;t a metaphor. It was
simply an archaic political term for what it is like living in a world in
which machines that you can&apos;t understand and you can&apos;t modify and you can&apos;t do
anything about, control you and everybody else.&quot; - Eben Moglen,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262542289/coding-democracy/&quot;&gt;Coding Democracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Facebook user count is approaching three billion. To help this trend
continue, Meta need to (among other things) maintain two critical assets; the
&lt;em&gt;secrecy&lt;/em&gt; of their algorithms and the restrictiveness of &lt;em&gt;interoperability&lt;/em&gt; with
their services. This is the game play for any budding technology company that is
yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should change that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How does the public stand to benefit from FLOSS?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;We need to rebuild our societies and institutions with a new ethos of
distributed power. It is our collective responsibility.&quot; - Webb,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262542289/coding-democracy/&quot;&gt;Coding Democracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia heralds this movement in a modern day technology landscape. It has
become a collective treasure, providing free encyclopedic information to those
with means of access (a lot more than the amount who can afford or access
books). It has survived its initial period where accuracy and validity of
information on Wikipedia was in question, and has solidified itself as an
&lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/book/4956/Wikipedia-20Stories-of-an-Incomplete-Revolution&quot;&gt;accepted academic tool&lt;/a&gt;
and public good alike, becoming the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/1201880/most-visited-websites-worldwide/&quot;&gt;7th most accessed website globally&lt;/a&gt;
after Google, Youtube, Facebook and some top porn sites (who knew free education
could be so exciting?). Additionally, it finished 2021 with a net surplus of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/foundation/1/1e/Wikimedia_Foundation_FY2020-2021_Audit_Report.pdf&quot;&gt;$87.6 million USD in cash&lt;/a&gt;
which supports further public good initiatives of the Wikimedia foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is safe to argue that in this case, CBP (commons-based production) has proven
itself as a benefit to the world community. Society gets free access to reliable
information (a cornerstone for prosperity in general) without being sold to
advertisers, Wikimedia can sustain operations with a solid financial margin, and
the volunteers of Wikipedia can feel pride in having contributed to a genuine
public good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When secrecy, restrictiveness and focus on profit are brought together, they
create a strong corrupting force. CBP activities such as Wikipedia are counter
to this.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/book/4956/chapter/1879816/From-Utopia-to-Practice-and-Back&quot;&gt;They focus more on a collective effort to achieve a public good and do so in the absence of market relations and hierarchies&lt;/a&gt;
while also providing positive psychological health benefits
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0167487012001456&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/10.1007/s10902-020-00242-8&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) (such as increase
in self worth to those who volunteer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where does FLOSS fit in? As well as involving the same flat hierarchical,
volunteer based structure, FLOSS development results in technology that more
often than not has interoperability and respect for the user&apos;s privacy at
heart - the antithesis of Big Tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Instead, if we could have a future where the person in charge changed from
time to time, and no one was fully in charge and everyone had to look over
their shoulder in trepidation of the competition taking users and suppliers by
offering them a better deal, it would be a better future. The key to this
though would have to be interoperability, as there needs to be a way for users
to easily move from one service to another. The network effect needs to be
eradicated as a growth function.&quot; - Cory Doctorow on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://changelog.com/podcast/535&quot;&gt;The Changelog, 01:00:00&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interoperability is a particularly juicy Achilles heel of what Cory Doctorow and
Rebeca Giblin call &quot;chokepoint capitalism&quot;, which illustrates the point of
capitalism&apos;s narrative that we currently find ourselves in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the present day reality of a farmer who needs to do a quick repair to
her tractor. But it is a modern day tractor from colossal agriculture machinery
manufacturer, Jon Deere, so the farmer is &quot;out of luck&quot; (unless, as of 2024, she
lives in Colorado, USA
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ifixit.com/News/73291/colorado-approves-first-ever-agricultural-right-to-repair-bill&quot;&gt;where the new Agriculture Right-to-Repair act has been passed!&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;br /&gt;
She is barred from doing this repair herself by DRM (Digital Rights Management) protected
software, meaning that even if she knows how to install the part, she doesn&apos;t have
the authority to activate it. Jon Deere charge $230, plus $130 an hour for a technician
to drive out and plug a cable into the tractor to authorize the part (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262542289/coding-democracy/&quot;&gt;src&lt;/a&gt;).
This is expensive enough, but what if the impending hail storm over the horizon arrives
before the technician does, destroying the crop entirely? Chokepoint capitalism is
when the corporations control the buyers, the sellers and the middle people (mechanics,
vendors, etc). They can do this in a large part because they deliberately deny interoperability
with their products, locking all parties into a system they control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily for the farmer though, there is a project
&lt;a href=&quot;https://tractorhacking.github.io/&quot;&gt;dedicated to circumventing the Jon Deere software locks&lt;/a&gt;,
so her crop is saved (although she risks a hefty fine for breaking the law by
repairing her tractor, even though she bought it outright). The right to repair
embodies the critical importance of interoperability in that without it, we are
beholden to the company whose product we use. With interoperability, the
companies are beholden to the public. It creates a need for companies to offer
the best service in order to maintain their customers. It shifts the balance of
power back towards the consumer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of interoperability echos in the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/society/20220413STO27211/usb-type-c-to-become-eu-s-common-charger-by-end-of-2024&quot;&gt;European Union&apos;s regulation&lt;/a&gt;
that by the end of 2024 all manufacturers of small electronic devices must use
USB-C for charging. Additionally consumers must be given the choice to buy a
device with or without a charger. This is interoperability on a hardware level,
but it illustrates the same fundamental point; technologies must work together
and we should be enabled, not restricted, by them - &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; if we, the
consumer, being restricted means profit for some person or faceless corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Focus on Communication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated at the beginning of this essay; software interfaces with our lives so
frequently, that it becomes harder and harder to distinguish a segregation
between what is, and what is not software driven. There is perhaps no better
example of this, than communication. How we communicate with each other has
undergone rapid and profound change leading us into an era where digital
communication is the preferred method, and messaging over voice a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ourworldindata.org/rise-of-social-media&quot;&gt;clear winner on top&lt;/a&gt;. Social
media lends itself well to this preference, offering both personal, group and
public communication channels. As such it saw huge adoption, the product coming
out on top being Facebook. But Facebook&apos;s end game was not just to offer the
best service to communicate and &quot;be social&quot;, that was just the honey trap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of social media platforms, with Myspace setting the scene,
the value of selling user data to generate advertisement revenue was clear.
Whether or not this was or is the motive from the start is secondary; the
prospect of huge earnings or acquiring power (usually the two coincide) is a
corrupting force. Period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Facebook originally claimed - as an alternative to MySpace - that they would
never process your data. They later had a referendum, asking users if they
would be OK to have their data processed (spied on). Users said no, Facebook
did it anyway.&quot; Cory Doctorow
&lt;a href=&quot;https://changelog.com/podcast/535&quot;&gt;The Changelog, 01:08:00&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This corruption has lead to disastrous consequences, the Cambridge Analytica
scandal taking a sizeable portion of the proverbial cake. What makes this even
worse is of course the fact that users are algorithmically served up content
which is calculated to achieve the most &quot;engagement&quot;, thus keeping them on the
platform longer and producing more data for Facebook to sell. Documentaries such
as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesocialdilemma.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Social Dilemma&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as well as whistle
blowers like Frances Haugen and Tristan Harris have helped to hoist up the optic
fiber veil that Big Tech would prefer to leave firmly in place. Our network
effect lock-in (no interoperability for Facebook users to communicate with
Twitter users for example) &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; descent into social and political chaos, is
their profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Just delete your Facebook account&quot; is a common phrase and fundamentally good
advice. Jarod Lannier communicates this with excellent clarity and wit in his
book,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/37830765-ten-arguments-for-deleting-your-social-media-accounts-right-now&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ten Arguments for Deleting Your Social Media Accounts Right Now&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
But for every one of us who commits and finally does so, there are x young
children signing up for new accounts who have little to no idea about the dark
reality they are stepping into. Simply limping away from this social catastrophe
and dragging a few out with you does not bring lasting change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A New Hope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the greater public goods that Elon Musk has yet to bring is the near
total destruction of Twitter. His shameful treatment of employees and other such
behaviours spawned a significant movement to decentralised social media
platforms. Mastodon attained the greatest uptake, seeing a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mastodon.online/@mastodonmigration/109368733146867283&quot;&gt;quarter million people sign up&lt;/a&gt;
on the day Elon Musk&apos;s acquisition of Twitter was settled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mastodon is a FLOSS project and implements the W3C&apos;s ActivityPub protocol. What
this enables on a functional basis is what centralised social media platforms
like Facebook actively want to restrict. Firstly, anyone can host a Mastodon
&quot;instance&quot;, essentially meaning a website on the internet that other users can
create accounts on. &lt;em&gt;All&lt;/em&gt; users on &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; instances can interact with each other
(i.e, all instances are interoperable with each other). And secondly, the
project is FLOSS and uses an established internet standard (ActivityPub) that is
maintained by the W3C who are in charge of all the standards that run the web.
In other words, you&apos;re free to build your social connections free of influence
from corporations, and to build it on top of an open and non-profit stack of
technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the beauties of Mastodon (and any other application built on
ActivityPub), is that if the instance you are registered with, departs from your
values (for example by attracting and supporting content and people you want no
part of), you can simply leave, register with a different instance and transfer
all your friend connections across. Your friends will not notice any practical
difference when interacting with you. There is no network effect lock-in, no
hidden algorithm, no advertisements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, as Mastodon communicates using the ActivityPub protocol, it is able
to interface with &lt;em&gt;any other service&lt;/em&gt; that uses ActivityPub, such as PeerTube (a
decentralised video streaming platform), GNU Social (social networking), Pleroma
(microblogging), and many more. With a technical model like this, services and
platforms help each other by existing within the same ecosystem. Users of one
ActivityPub based service help all others &lt;em&gt;equally&lt;/em&gt; with every user that signs
up. A community of communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FLOSS is a system of production that has the power not only to create public
goods like a free and academically valid encyclopedia, and social media without
surveillance and calculated manipulation, but to offer these goods on a
collective scale that can upend the power that Big Tech has over society. Not
one app to rule them all, but many apps that work together to rule over no one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaboration and volunteering are two of the most prominent vertebra in
humanity&apos;s collective back bone. It binds communities together, a common proof
is when natural disasters strike. Everyone works together to help each other,
afterwards becoming more tightly knit. It is innate within us, and we feel good
when we do it. It is just that for the last fifteen years we have been trying to
build and maintain communities inside a Skinner box that invisibly promotes a
delicate balance of social and antisocial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://direct.mit.edu/books/book/4956/chapter/1879816/From-Utopia-to-Practice-and-Back&quot;&gt;FLOSS projects are not impervious to issues&lt;/a&gt;
, but they do begin with a different set of values. They are built by a
community on a volunteer basis. The better the community, i.e developers,
documentation writers, content creators and users alike, feel about the product
or service, the more they will want to help and the more financial donations
they will give or receive; therein, lightening the workload, reducing the market
share of corporate competition, and supporting the community further. Around and
around it goes. In this space, the community has a collective power. No singular
entity can steer the ship down the river of corruption, moral fraud,
surveillance and manipulation with much certainty. The community will more than
likely dispute it, and if the collective opinion is ignored, they may well
&quot;fork&quot; the project (to clone a copy and develop it independently of the
original, a common process in FLOSS) and continue with the original plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This exact scenario happened in April 2023 where the Rust Foundation, who guide
the increasingly popular and fast growing programming language, issued a request
for comment on a policy change. The policy change dictated many non-FLOSS values
and the Rust community responded in outrage, which saw a group of users fork the
Rust project, renaming it to Crab (the Rust logo is a cartoon crab). The Rust
foundation received the notice
&lt;a href=&quot;https://foundation.rust-lang.org/news/rust-trademark-policy-draft-revision-next-steps/&quot;&gt;loud and clear&lt;/a&gt;.
A similar event happened in 2022 when the IRC Freenode server
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/joepie91/df80d8d36cd9d1bde46ba018af497409&quot;&gt;got taken over by a rogue moderator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Doctorow&apos;s previous quote also shows, Mark Zuckerberg (the main moderator of
Facebook), went rogue quite a while ago. Unfortunately, we can not fork
Facebook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&quot;Facebook originally claimed - as an alternative to MySpace - that they would
never process your data. They later had a referendum, asking users if they
would be OK to have their data processed (spied on). Users said no, Facebook
did it anyway.&quot; Cory Doctorow
&lt;a href=&quot;https://changelog.com/podcast/535&quot;&gt;The Changelog, 01:08:00&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FLOSS helps community because it is built, owned and managed by community; the
power is with the people, not a singular person or corporate entity. This
changes the motivations behind technical and design decisions, making
interoperability in particular, a natural choice. It helps promote social and
interpersonal benefits by means of collaborating with each other for a public
good, and can result in tools that not only function better, respect the
fundamental freedoms of users and remain accessible across the wealth divide,
but which can also help communicate to government and industry what a partial
antidote to social catastrophe can look like.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>open-source</category><category>society</category></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>https://tjex.net/posts/hello-world/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tjex.net/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>It&apos;s traditional.</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 10:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Why am I starting to blog?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to learn more concretely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to be more critical of my thoughts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to hopefully contribute positively to someone else&apos;s knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to make a point to myself, that will otherwise keep mutating in my head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to support a cultural and societal divergence from centralised social media&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if people actually get to this blog...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to test my ideas against the chaos of the internet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s see...&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>